A Guide to the Frank Richard Stockton Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #5866
Frank Richard Stockton Collection 1875-1900
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
5866
54 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift 1958 Jun 5
Item Listing
- Manuscript
  - The Adventures of Captain Horn, 1895; TMs, 582 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections; in slipcase.]
- Letters
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1876 Nov 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Instructs him to have 2 Ferris blocks engraved as soon as they come in; suggest having 2 engravers do them as they must be ready in January.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 Jan 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for notes and favors; instructs him how to forward his mail to Philadelphia; mentions article that will appear in the Midsummer number, a "Letter-Box" item by the daughter of Benson John Lossing, and Amalie LaForge. ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, [1877 Jan]; AL, 4 p.
    [Apologizes for sending the proofs late; points out that he introduced "
    The Baby Camel
    , " "
    Prairie-dog's Home
    , " and "
    Prairie Wolf
    "; criticizes animal drawing by [William Holbrook] Beard and specifies 3 drawings he disagrees with, should any pictures have to be omitted.] (incomplete)
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 Mar 28; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he had a delightful trip to the Bahamas and is enjoying Florida; reports on letters lost in forwarding; inquires about fees for "
    Sam Clemson
    " and "
    The Lion
    "; asks for reading material to be sent to him in Jacksonville; sends regards to "immortals of 743"; says he is anxious to see
    St. Nicholas
    magazine which he cannot get in Florida. ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 May 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of manuscripts which he will revise; inquires about the $100 English serial he is to revise; declines invitation to Carnival; asks him to come see a permanent exhibition in Philadelphia, 1905 Broad St.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 Jul 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Returns a corrected, shortened proof; refers to a Russian story in the possession of Mary Mapes Dodge; mentions batch of electro-work he sent to Clarke and his need of money.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 Jul 31; ALS, 1 p.
    [Includes two 1 1/2 page manuscripts requested by [Mary Mapes] Dodge; mentions that he has 3 Scannell pictures, but no manuscript yet.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Mr. Scott, 1877 Aug 30; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refers to revised manuscripts he has sent to William Fayal Clarke's office, the charge being $53; asks him to hand Clarke a letter when he returns from vacation.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton, steamer " City of Illinois, " off Cape Cod, to William Fayal Clarke, 1877 Sep 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he is leaving for Europe rather suddenly without having revised manuscripts; advises him to repage and shorten them; discusses social matters.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 May 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends requested address; promises to write about schedules, etc.; wants drawing of the expression on a boy's face, which is to appear changed in a story.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 May 27; ALS, 2 p.
    [Speaks about a frontispiece which he finds improved; leaves the execution of his ideas, by process or wood, to Alexander William Drake; says he will discuss "schedule" when coming in on Wednesday.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Talks about stories and illustrations to appear in
    agrees to some formats and suggests some changes; leaves decision about frontispiece to Alexander Wilson Drake. ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1890 Nov 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he will have requested story by mid-December and it will be divided into 5 chapters of about 2000 words each.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 Jun 1; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses changes and omissions on proof for July; mentions contributors Trowbridge, Dodge, Richards, and Foote.] (On St. Nicholas stationary)
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 Jul 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Announces his visit for July 3.] (On St. Nicholas stationary)
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 Jul 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Endorses a note to [Mary Mapes] Dodge; requests to be sent all manuscripts that have to be read; says he has time for manuscript work right now.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 Sep 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of proofs; says they will be take care of promptly.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1878 Sep 15; ALS, 4 p.
    [Criticizes proof of a portrait; finds it worse that the photograph; makes suggestions for the January edition of "A. J. F." in regard to manuscripts and drawings; talks about the December edition; suggests insertions; feels upset about rumors regarding his health; says he won the championship-badge at the Archery Club; writes with a quill from an eagle's wing and promises to send such a quill to him.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton, Philadelphia, to William Fayal Clarke, 1880 May 19; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he will leave for Charlottesville, Virginia next week; gives instructions for forwarding the valise with manuscripts via Adam's Express, which is faster and more reliable than United States[mail]; feels ill; intends to spend time in the Blue Ridge Mountains; promises to send the electro-stories; asks if the new edition of
    Rudder Grange
    has appeared.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton, Venice, Italy, to William Fayal Clarke, 1883 Jul 1; ALS, 3 p.
    [Wonders if his mail has been sent to Europe; misses the June number of
    reports on his illness in Florida; finds Venice enchanting, urges him to take his bride there; mentions letter his wife received from [Mary Mapes] Dodge; asks if he ought to do more for
    requests Mr. Smith's address; states that letters sent to him have been lost.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton, Geneva, to William Fayal Clarke, 1883 Aug 18; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets that he did not write
    The Lion and the Lamb
    , which he received a request for a copy of; talks about David Douglas' idea to publish his collected short stories; mentions a check Douglas sent him before he sold a single copy of
    recalls meeting him in Florence; mentions suggestion to write "The Candid Adventurer," but does not feel up to it.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, 1883 Sep 16; ALS, 4 p.
    [Talks about their travels through Switzerland, their 2 days on the Rigi, their plans a trip to the Rhine, England, and Scotland, and then home to America; says he will write requested article and furnish photographs; mentions idea for serial story, set in Rome, Venice and various parts of Italy and Switzerland, for children, for
    if the publishers want it; looks forward to promised letter; mentions having spent several days wit Mr. and Mrs. Roswell Smith and Dr. Robinson.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to John Eliot Bowen, 1883 Nov 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says the Century Company's request for an occasional story for
    The Independent
    cannot be complied with at once, because he is otherwise engaged; promises to write a story of 8 to 10 columns when time allows; asks fee of $100 for a story of that length.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to John Eliot Bowen, 1883 Dec 31; ALS, 1 p.
    [Encloses "
    A Penny Walk
    " for
    instructs him on where to divide the story should it be necessary to publish it in 2 installments; hopes story will be liked.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1884 Nov 25; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets not being able to meet him at this time; says he will be back in New York the following week and spend the winter there; promises a humorous story for February, if not sooner.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1885 Feb 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Authorizes him to deposit Stockton's vote of favor of admitting William Fayal Clarke to membership, as he is unable to attend the Author's Club meeting.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1885 Nov 4; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses disappointment that an important part of the manuscript
    The Demon Plague
    was lost while in McClure's possession; includes attempted replacement which was exceedingly difficult to write; discusses another sketch; points out where his portrait, to accompany the sketch, can be obtained.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Henry Rideing, 1887 Jul 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks him to send a proof to his new house in Madison, New Jersey and to come visit there when he comes that way.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Messrs. Sampson, Low & Co., 1887 Jul 12; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks the company for letter containing royalty accounts and money; refers to
    The Dusantes
    which appears in 3 parts in
    The Century
    assumes the story will be printed by the Century Company in book form in 1888; wishes the company luck with his books; acknowledges receipt of copies of his books; says he is pleased by their appearance.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1889 Jan 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends note to accompany paragraph for the McClure column.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Editor, The Eagle, 1889 Nov 21; LS, 1 p.
    [Asks for the correction of a statement in a New York paper in regard to his travel intentions.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1889 Dec 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs him that he is unable to go to Chicago to read; promises to send an item for McClure syndicate; sends New Year's wishes.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1890 Mar 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is unable to attend copyright meeting; promises to come to the next meeting on a Club-dinner night at the Aldine.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1890 Jun 24; LS, 1 p.
    [Promises to write a Christmas story for him, although he is very busy with
    The Squirrel Inn
    mentions "
    The Illinois Farmer
    " by Johnson.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1890 Oct 25; LS, 1 p.
    [Writes children's stories only occasionally now but is willing to write a ten thousand word piece for McClure's circular for $500; compliments him on his magazine for young people.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1891 Mar 6; ALS, 3 p.
    [Congratulates him on the copyright victory; says that the authors of America owe Johnson everlasting gratitude; declares himself proud to be a citizen of the United States. ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1891 Apr 11; ALS, 4 p.
    [Tells him that he has not been asked by anyone to take part in the reading on the 22nd; says he will be happy read, but only parts of
    Squirrel Inn
    says the same presentation was like by another audience; refers to European trip; congratulates him on hors received from France. ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Mr. Robinson, 1892 Jan 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs him that he will have to get permission to use
    The Great War Syndicate
    from Messrs. Dodd & Mead; says he has talked to them about the matter.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1893 Jan 18; TLS, 1 p.
    [Refers to a will, with property bequeathed to Stockton; explains how much he expects to get and what percentage should go to Johnson.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1893 Feb 14; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses will of Stockton's great great great grandfather from New Jersey; says it is authentic, but no possessions come with it and Johnson will get nothing in return for his endeavors.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1896 Apr 14; LS, 1 p.
    [Regrets not having been able to attend the meeting of the Council of the Copyright League; says he is enjoying culinary and other delights of the Bayou country; intends to return to New Jersey by May 1.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Mrs. Frederick Gotthold, 1897 Aug 19; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Responds to request for his help in manning the Gotthold houseboat; suggests "The Halcyon," and "The Angler."]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to E. Leslie Gilliams, 1897 Sep 24; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends manuscript of "
    A Sailor's Knot
    " for $850, giving him all the serial rights in the United States in Europe with the stipulation not to offer it to American monthlies; says the story had been written for
    Ladies Home Journal
    of Philadelphia; says he took it back after a disagreement with the editor.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Professor [Harry Thurston] Peck, 1898 Oct 21; TLS, 1 p.
    [Agrees to lend a hand in the compilation of the
    New Library of Literature
    , provided the new duties will not interfere with his present engagements; says he cannot do any editorial work, only assist in choosing authors for the series.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to John Brisben Walker, 1900 Aug 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests payment of $500 for "
    The Conscious Armada
    , " published in
    Cosmopolitan
    in June; reminds him of the terms agreed upon; says that if "
    " was shorter than average, it was evened out by "
    The Cot and the Rill
    " which was much longer than average; insists on $500 for each story published.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1900 Nov 5; TLS, 2 p.
    [Relates a strange dream, pertaining to his writing of humorous stories; comments on letter from Johnson, received the day after the dream, in which Johnson requests another humorous story; says he is glad that Johnson liked
    Pomona's Travels
    , he is pleased with illustrations by Mr. Steele.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Samuel Sidney McClure, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests meeting to discuss story, ready to print, of about 30800 words; says it could be divided into 5 segments to be published in newspapers; asks to see a notice from the
    Commercial Advertiser
    . ]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to William Fayal Clarke, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is in bed "with a ten pound boil"; expects to be all right soon; asks him to keep his mail in the office unless something looks very important.]
  - Frank Richard Stockton to Kate Douglas Wiggins Riggs, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets not being able to come to a benefit in New York; hopes to get better acquainted with Mr. Riggs in the future.]
- Photographs and Prints
  - Frank Richard Stockton, profile, by T. Johnson, [1886]; Engraving
  - Magazine photographs, Frank Richard Stockton, head and shoulders, Photos 3 copies
- Miscellaneous
  - Quotation from " The Lady or the Tiger ", 1892 Feb 19; AQ,
    ["Without the slightest hesitation.. ."]
  - Signed note regarding International Copyright Law, n. d.; Printed note